Over the years,
I've made a lot of viral videos.
I even had one on TikTok where a single
reel gained me over a million followers.
And I've had some pretty big hitters on
YouTube, too.
A video I did on whether
or not you should try Whoop has paid me
18,462 pounds. A video I did on whether
or not
Prime is bullshit, 4,626
pounds.
And I also made a video on whether
or not AG1 is any good,
4,566 pounds. To make viral videos,
you get paid well.
And the reason you're probably wondering
why Whoop pays so much more is Whoop is
paying YouTube for the ads on that video.
It makes you think, if Whoop
are going to pay
that much money for an ad, they're
making way more money back from it.
This is known as ROAS, return on ad spend.
Some of you might be wondering why,
over the last year,
I have not made any viral
videos.
But it's because I fell into a trap,
a trap that many creators fall into.
Some people don't even know about it,
and actually,
some of you watching this are
falling right into it right now,
and I may just snap you out of it.
Social media can actually be played in two
different modes, and some
people are even blissfully unaware of
this, and especially
if they're just copying
other people,
they can make the same mistake
that I made for years.
Some people's number one priority
is views.
And there are some creators
that do well from this, like MrBeast.
He quite literally needs the views,
not only to get paid from his sponsors,
but
also to get paid by AdSense. With
that money,
he then reinvests into creating a new
video. Now,
here are some negatives of optimizing for
views.
It's incredibly stressful.
If you're making a video
and you put weeks, maybe even a
month into it,
and you get different editors
and you pay lots of money, and you
have to go to extreme amounts of effort
and the video bombs,
you might not just not
make money, you might lose money. You
are the lowest paid in the ecosystem.
You think the sponsor on your video
is making the most money because they're
making
money from the ads. Google, well,
is making a fuck ton of money anyway.
Then you just get given a little bit of
what's left.
"Hey, this was a profitable ecosystem.
Here, creator,
have a few cents on the dollar."
But the worst thing that you're
going to get from this,
something called a subprime audience.
I was working with a creator who
was trying to grow his email list,
and he said,
"James,
I'm thinking of maybe giving everyone a
free mug if they join my email
list." And I said, "Yeah,
that sounds great,
but there's one problem.
You might then end up with an email list
full of people that just wanted a free
mug." You go to sell them something,
and they'll go, "No, thanks, mate.
Just needed a mug." I
was growing my YouTube, and I'll admit,
I fell into the trap
of I just wanted a big YouTube channel.
But having a big YouTube channel with over
400,000 subscribers was like being a
priest with a massive cock.
If you're not going to do anything
productive with it,
is it really that great? Well, actually,
yeah.
We know priests find things to do with
their cocks, and often little boys,
allegedly. It was only
when we released Nutonic
that I promoted it on YouTube.
People were like, "Shut up
and go make another viral video." I
was optimized
for views and getting
that gold play button.
And to be honest,
I kind of just wanted to be treated like a
YouTuber with over a
million subscribers.
Then you get invited on podcasts because
they go, "We'll get
James on the podcast because he's got a
million subscribers.
His audience will see him in the
thumbnail, and they'll click."
If you want to
optimize for views, that's great.
But I've done it,
and there's a better way.
I'm going to get into that now.
You optimize the channel for clients.
When I first got into social media,
it wasn't for clout, fame, recognition.
It was to get more clients. I
was a personal trainer.
I was in the gym,
and I didn't really enjoy walking the
floor.
I'd walk up, "Hey, mate,
can I just give you a little tip on
the..." "Shut the fuck
up." "Yeah, cool, mate.
You have a good day, buddy."
And I thought, if I just post
helpful content on social media,
then come the end of the day,
someone might DM me
and go, "Hey, what are your prices?
Can I have a consultation?"
And even a crazy thing
that I figured out over the
last few months is
that some of my lowest viewed videos
produce me the most
amount of revenue because I'm optimizing
the video to convert the viewer into
considering doing business with me,
not making a video that is
just there to get views and go viral.
I can be more specific with the content.
If you want to go viral with content,
it has to appeal to everyone,
to the masses.
And there's something
that I would call ROI content,
return on investment.
Over here, people
are just getting entertainment from
content, which is cool.
But if at any point you bore them
or you take too long
or you're laboring the
point, they fuck off.
And here's a little trick for any of you
getting into social
media. Everyone hates you.
No one likes you until they do.
So if it's your first time appearing on
someone's screen and you say something
that
you think is cheeky,
they're just going to go, "Twat."
But where I've started
making content to try and get clients,
I know that whatever I'm putting out is
going to give them return on investment.
If you listen and go through all of my
videos, come the end of it, your
business and your sales process will
perform better, which will make you more
money. And at the end of the day,
you might think I'm a legend,
not because of who
I am, but because of how I helped you.
So many people are coming onto social
media,
and they're being drawn into the world
of just optimizing for views. But really,
the main reason we get on social media is
to try and get more clients.
When it comes to creating content, it
is important
that you work backwards.
First thing you need
is to know the problems that your
clients face,
and these need to be well understood.
This is why if you want to go online in
any business, you must have some
face-to-face experience because you
understand their problems.
Even Declan here, my editor, he,
through working with people,
holding a camera,
and being involved in their process,
will understand the problems.
And the problems are important because we
must flip them into hooks.
And the hooks,
the first one to three seconds.
Tell me a problem
that someone's faced
that you've worked with, Declan. Not PT.
Think of videography.
So your problem would be overexposed.
And for any of you that don't know,
that pretty much means
that the footage that
you have is too bright.
So then we can start looking into that.
As a form of hook, we go verbal.
Does your content keep coming out
looking like this? Visual. In
that first bit of footage, we're going to
overexpose it. Cool.
So what we would do
is maybe as part of the visual, we would
get the camera, we'd put it in manual,
we would then crank up the exposure so
it's
brightest. It would give
that plus three reading on the bottom.
So the verbal hook would be,
does your content keep coming out looking
like this?
Then the second part of the hook,
which could technically be a setup,
we could say
something like, here are three ways
that you could correct it to make it look
like
this. Then we go another visual,
and it's perfect.
Then we go into point one, point two,
point three, and then an outro.
Now, just before we get into these points,
something that I think is really cool to
do, with your outro, don't say, "And
if you followed me, you would
know that." Don't say,
"If you subscribe to my channel, it would
make me happy." Just say something like in
short-form content, "I'll see you
tomorrow." Because they'll go, "No,
you won't. I don't follow you.
Oh, but if I followed you,
maybe I would." You could even say
something like, "Oh,
guys, in the next video,
we're going to cover off X.
Can't wait to do it." Now,
when explaining your points,
I did actually learn this
from Ed.
He has something called the dangle.
So what are three ways, Declan,
we could fix someone's exposure? Lovely.
Love an ND filter. An ND filter
is a pair of sunglasses for your camera,
for any of
you that don't know. Lets less light in,
so we can lower the F-stop and get more of
that blurry background. So the dangle
is pretty much where we do point one,
we dangle point three,
and then we do point two.
So for instance, you'd go, it
is really important
that you get an ND filter for
your camera. And not only
is it going to make the picture look
better, it's going
to protect your lens. Now,
just before I tell you why it's imperative
that you film
in shade,
we need to look at the settings
that you need to change in your camera.
And what we're doing there
is we're jumping a step to build their
intrigue into
what is to come so they have a reason to
stay for stage two.
This type of content might not go viral
because only a small subset
niche of people care about exposure
or even know what it is.
However, you present this video, they go,
"Good bloody gosh, that man knows a
lot about videography." You get this in
front of someone five, six, seven times,
they're starting to consider doing
business with you.
By the time they've watched an hour of
your content, they're thinking, "How do I
give this person some money?" Okay,
now Declan, let's go from a personal
training standpoint. What
is a problem that some of your clients
faced?
Okay, so the problem is squat depth.
So first hook,
let's go for a question Okay, so the hook,
we're going
to go for a question hook. Why
is it some people can squat to full depth
whilst
other people struggle to even break past
parallel?
All right, can we go for a visual?
And it's going to have to be B-roll.
And for any of you that don't know,
B-roll is footage that you film, and you
overlay it over your A-roll. The A-roll
is this right now.
Technically, this is our B footage.
Would you say this is B footage?
So when people say B-roll, it means
that you'd then go into the gym,
you would film
different things, you'd overlay it.
Because then whilst they're listening to
the verbal hook, they get the visual of
the exact thing you're talking about.
We get to paint two things at the same
time.
Again,
we could then say we'll use the same
structure.
So we have that initial hook. Why
is it that some people can squat to full
depth
while other people just can't get past
parallel?
In this video,
I'm going to allow you to squat deeper.
And the best part is you can do it in a
day. Got to go raise heels.
What else would you say? A widened stance.
What's it called when you sit in a squat?
Let's just call it a squat hold.
So again, we could go into number one.
If you raise your heels,
you can artificially create mobility in
the ankle.
This will allow you to sit deeper.
This allows your shin bone to lean forward
more,
which allows your femur to come lower,
which allows, even though you wouldn't use
those anatomical words.
But just before we get into a stretch
that can
revolutionize your squat,
let's quickly look into the stance of your
feet.
Again, [chuckles] we could try the dangle,
go back, and then the outro again.
If you enjoyed this video,
you're going to love my next one,
whatever it is.
However, at the same time,
I'm going to be a bit of a hypocrite.
I've been giving people advice as to where
some people do get a bit
too guilty of trying to bundle too much
information into one video.
So for any of you out there that
are struggling with content frequency,
this is
what I would recommend you do.
You map out the piece of content exactly
like we're
doing here, but instead, we
are going to create this section here.
Why is it that some people can squat all
the way down and other people, they can
only reach parallel?
That's a block hook visual
that we can use at the
beginning of the reel.
Then for reel number one,
next time you're in the gym, try
raising your heels
and sitting into a squat.
You'll find it a lot easier,
and you can get deeper.
This is great because this
is going to allow us to take the
quadriceps through a
longer range of motion.
That's the reel done.
Then next week,
you use this exact same block again.
You recycle it,
but you go into the next video.
Why is it that some people can squat all
the way down, but other people only make
it halfway? Well, did you know
that widening your stance means
that your femurs can
be a bit wider,
permitting a little gap for you to sit
into?
If your feet are too narrow,
you quite literally do not have the hip
angles and
structure to provide enough space for you
to sit into.
So next time you visit the gym,
try widening your foot stance.
See you tomorrow.
And again, you get the drift.
We can then reuse
that same packaging again.
And again, go into the squat hold.
Did you know there is a stretch
that you could
do,
and if you'd only do it every day for
three minutes, you could end up squatting
deeper than a seven-year-old Asian girl
before you know it?
This stuff is great to plan out,
is great to get good at.
The second you can work backwards from
people's problems, you are optimizing not
for views, but they will come,
but to solve problems.
Think of it this way.
Me right now making these videos for you,
I'm trying to knock off
so many of your problems out your life
that eventually you just get to a point
where you go, "You son of a bitch, I'm in.
Whatever you're selling, James,
I'm in." There's links in the description.
Don't worry. Now, the next trap
that people fall into is they think
that content
turns into clients. It does, but not yet.
So just to reiterate,
we create content that
is optimized for clients,
not for views. You can be famous,
but you can be broke.
Alternatively,
you can have loads of clients,
and you can be rich.
No one knows who you are.
But then we must optimize content for one
thing.
What's that thing, Declan? Data. Come on,
man.
If you're ever going to leave me
or negotiate a price rise on your salary,
you're
going to need this.
So you're making this amazing content.
You're working backwards from people's
problems.
The next thing you need to think about
is how can you get their data.
So at the end of
that first piece of content, and
if you want to make sure that
your content is never exposed again,
comment the word bright, and I will
send you over a free guide
that makes sure that your content
is perfectly exposed
for the rest of your life.
That chatbot sounded good, didn't it?
Then what was the other problem?
Squat depth.
If you comment the word squat,
over the next 10 days,
I'm going to be sending you
10 ways to improve your squats
and some other variations I guarantee
you've never
done,
and you can incorporate them into your
program and not only reap the benefits
but the enjoyability of variation in your
training program.
So just comment the word squat,
and I'll send it over to you.
And in return,
you create content where people know
that you can solve their
problems. And here's the thing.
If you post 100 pieces of content,
you will start
to see patterns into
that to see what emerges on top.
Wow, when I spoke about this,
I got way more views than here. Cool.
There must be more interest in there.
I'm going to delve into it.
I'm going to talk about F-stop, exposure.
What's the other one?
Frame rates, shutter speeds, audio.
And then every single piece of content you
put out can get you some form of data.
Once you've got their emails,
you can put them in some kind of sequence
where you
continue to solve problems. But this time,
they're not having to go on Instagram
and scroll through 100 videos before
stumbling across one of yours and going,
"Wow,
that's an interesting thing I never
thought of." They're going to get it sent
daily
by email or weekly as part of a
newsletter, and they're going to go, "Wow,
this
guy, Declan,
I started watching his content.
He solved so many problems that I had.
So then I ended up commenting on one of
his posts.
So I then joined his email newsletter.
Every day, there's an email
that comes through that's absolutely
fire." And
now one day comes through one of your
social media posts fucked
up, or you went to do a squat session
and hated it.
Before you know it,
you're on his landing page.
On the landing page, you get clients.
I know it can seem like I repeat myself
here, people. So imagine 1,000 views.
You get 100 emails.
20 people visit your landing page.
You get one new client.
If you're a PT, one new client to you
is worth thousands of pounds or dollars.
So next time you're out there creating
content, it is imperative that you do not
optimize content to go viral
or to get views.
I did it for years, and it's all right.
It pays the bills.
But my God, when you turn up every day
and solve problems that people are facing,
they end up clicking the links in your
descriptions and joining your course.
And it pays way better. And it means
that on days that I've not got video ideas
that go viral,
I can just sit in front of camera like I
did today, riff for a bit,
and know that at the end of it,
I'll probably get 5
or 10 people join my program.
Really is that simple. Oh, and by the way,
if you enjoyed this video, you'll love
this one that YouTube's put here.
Highly recommend it